Guide to the William Force Stead Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Force Stead papers
1859-1968
1900-1940
OSB MSS 158
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
32.83
(75 boxes)
The William Force Stead Papers document the literary career and aspects of the personal life of poet, clergyman and scholar William Force Stead. The papers include personal and professional correspondence; writings; notebooks, personal papers and photographs; printed material; and documents relating to Stead's work as Honorary Secretary of the Keats-Shelley Memorial Association. The letters document aspects of Stead's literary and religious careers as well as his family relationships. Literary correspondents include Edmund Blunden, T. S. Eliot, William Golding, Frank Morley, Lady Ottoline Morrell, and W. B.Yeats. There are also letters by English composer Henry Vere Fitzroy Somerset. The collection contains drafts, manuscripts and typescripts of many works by Stead, including drafts of what appears to be an unpublished memoir. Personal papers include diaries from between 1896 and 1928; records of Stead's marriage and of his work for the U. S. Consular Service; and family photographs.
Stead, William Force, 1884-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Series I-VI purchased from Dom Julian Stead, and purchased from Wesleyan University Library, 1969; Series VII gift of Dom Julian Stead, 1974; Series VIII transferred from the Manuscript Department, University of Virginia Library, 1975; Series IX purchased from Frank Shivers, 1978; Series X gift of Dom Julian Stead, 1978.
T. S. Eliot letter to W. F. Stead, 1930 December 2, purchased from Gotham Book Mart, 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 68 (film reel): ‡a Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
William Force Stead, 1884-1967
William Force Stead was born in Washington DC in 1884. He attended the University of Virginia for several years, and in 1908 joined the United States Consular Service. From 1908 until 1915 he was a Vice-Consul in England, first in Nottingham and then in Liverpool. In 1911 he married Anne Frances Goldsborough in Baltimore, Maryland; the couple's first child, Philip, was born two years later. Their second son Peter was born in 1926.
Stead was ordained a minister in the Church of England in 1916, and served for two years as a curate at Ross-on-Wye. He received his B.A. in theology from Queen's College, Oxford in 1921, following which he was appointed Assistant Chaplain of the English Church in Florence, Italy. In 1926 Stead received an M.A. from Queen's College, and thereafter served as Chaplain of Worcester College, Oxford from 1926 to 1933. It was during this time that he baptized his friend, the American-born poet T. S. Eliot, into the Church of England. Stead's other literary friends included W. B. Yeats, Edmund Blunden, Richard Cobden-Sanderson, C. S. Lewis, and Robert Sencourt.
Between 1911 and 1933 Stead published seven volumes of poetry, including Windflowers (1911), Festival in Tuscany (1927), and Uriel: A Hymn in Praise of Divine Immanence (1933).
In August of 1933 Stead was received into the Roman Catholic Church by the English Dominican Bede Jarrett. Anne Stead had become a Catholic three years earlier, and spent much of her time in a convent in Birmingham. As a result of his conversion, Stead resigned from the Worcester College chaplaincy; he moved to the nearby village of Clifton Hampden. During the 1930s, Stead published anthololgies, magazine articles and reviews; wrote a B.Litt thesis on the works of the Jesuit poet Robert Southwell; and published the first edition of Christopher Smart's Jubiliate Agno.
Stead and his son Peter sailed for the United States on August 12, 1939 to visit relatives in Baltimore. World War II broke out before they could return to England, and their passports were canceled. Anne Stead remained in England throughout the war, choosing to remain close to their oldest child, Philip, who had proved to be mentally handicapped and was institutionalized.
Stead never lived in England again, although he visited several times after the war. From 1943 through 1958 he was Professor of English at Trinity College in Washington, DC, a Roman Catholic school for girls. In Baltimore, Stead met Nancy Howard DeFord Venable, a widow and literary hostess, and eventually shared her homes in Baltimore and St. Mâlo, France with her. The pair traveled frequently and entertained literary friends, including T. S. Eliot, W. H. Auden, William Golding, Vere Somerset, and Tennessee Williams. Stead's health and memory began to fail in the final years of his life, and he died in Nancy Venable's Baltimore home on March 8, 1967.
Scope and Contents
The William Force Stead Papers document the literary career, personal life, and religious vocation of poet, clergyman and scholar William Force Stead. The papers include personal and professional correspondence; writings; notebooks, personal papers and photographs; printed material; and documents relating to Stead's work as Honorary Secretary of the Keats-Shelley Memorial Association.
Series I through Series VI contain material acquired in 1969 and organized shortly thereafter into six series, while Series VII through X contain post-1969 acquisitions in order of acquisition, and Series XI contains printed material acquired at various times during the 1970s. For some types of material, therefore, it is necessary to consult several series.Correspondence is located in Series I, Correspondence, as well as in Series VII through Series X, while Stead's writings are located in Series II, Series III, and Series VII and Series X. Many of the items in Series XI, Printed Materials, are also works by Stead.
Correspondence includes extensive and detailed family correspondence with Stead's father, brother, and wife, Anne Frances Goldsborough Stead; letters from a number of English literary figures, including Edmund Blunden, T. S. Eliot, Frank Morley, Lady Ottoline Morrell, and W. B.Yeats, and English composer Henry Vere Fitzroy Somerset; and letters from a variety of scholarly and religious colleagues on personal and professional subjects. The Stead Papers also contain notes, drafts, and manuscripts and typescripts for many of Stead's works, particularly his poetry and his religious meditations; folders with titles beginning with "Stead" in Series II appear to contain draft chapters of an unpublished memoir. Other material of biographical interest includes several boxes of diaries; papers relating to Stead's consular service; and school notebooks, found in Series IV, as well as additional personal and family documentation in Series VII through Series X.
Arrangement
Organized into 11 series: I. Correspondence, 1900-1972. II. Writings, 1899-1963. III. Notebooks, 1876-1955. IV. Personal Papers, 1891-1967. V. Photographs, 1910-1935. VI. Keats-Shelley Memorial Association Papers, 1906-1950. VII. November 1974 Acquisition, 1848-1968. VIII. October 1975 Acquisition, 1978, undated. IX. May 1978 Acquisition, 1922-1948. X. December 1978 Acquisition, 1859-1960. XI. Printed Materials, 1900-1960.
American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors, English -- 20th Century; Catholic converts; Christian life; Clergy; English literature -- 20th Century; English poetry -- 20th Century; Religious poetry; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Diaries -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Diaries -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Authors; Clergy; Blunden, Edmund, 1896-1974; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Golding, William, 1911-1993; Morley, Frank, 1860-1937; Morrell, Ottoline Violet Anne Cavendish-Bentinck, Lady, 1873-1938; Stead, Anne Frances Goldsborough; Stead family; Stead, William Force, 1884-1967; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939; Church of England ( Clergy); Keats-Shelley Memorial Association
- Correspondence, 1900-1972; Series I; 6.26; (15 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is organized into three subseries, Literary Correspondence, General Correspondence and Family Correspondence, and each subseries is alphabetically arranged by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The letters document aspects of Stead's literary and religious careers as well as his family relationships. Literary correspondents include Edmund Blunden, T. S. Eliot, Frank Morley, Lady Ottoline Morrell, and W. B.Yeats.There are also letters by English composer Henry Vere Fitzroy Somerset. Literature, particularly poetry, and aspects of religious belief are frequent topics of the correspondence.
  This series contains only the correspondence which was acquired by purchase in 1969. Later acquisitions of Stead correspondence, mainly additional family letters, are located in Series VII, Series VIII, Series IX, and Series X.
  - Literary Correspondence
    - Abbott, Charles David, 1900-, 1938 February-March (Box 1)
    - Addison, Lewis Percy, 1933 April 4 (Box 1)
    - Ainsworth, Edward Gay, 1902-1940, 1938 July-August (Box 1)
    - Aldenham, Alban George Henry Gibbs, 2nd baron, 1846-1936, 1935 May 26 (Box 1)
    - Aldenham, Lillie Caroline (Houldsworth) Gibbs, baroness, d. 1950, undated (Box 1)
    - Aldington, Richard, 1892-1962, 1924 June (Box 1)
    - Alexander, Archibald, 1874-1942, 1933 April-May (Box 1)
    - Bangay, (Miss) Evelyn D., 1938 March (Box 1)
    - Bardin, James Cook, 1887-, 1909-1938 (Box 1)
    - Bardsley, Cyril Charles Bowman, bp. of Peterborough, 1870-1940, 1926 January (Box 1)
    - Baring-Gould, Harry, 1912 May (Box 1)
    - Beddoes, Vaughan Roscoe Minton, 1931 December (Box 1)
    - Bennett, Joan (Frankau), 1896-, 1935 November (Box 1)
    - Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1862-1925, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - Bethune-Baker, James Franklin, 1861-1951, 1921 February (Box 1)
    - Blunden, Edmund Charles, 1896-, 1920-1940; 3 (Box 1)
    - Blunden, Mary, 1927 February 18 (Box 1)
    - Boissevain, Eugen, undated (Box 1)
    - Bosanquet, Theodora, 1880-1961, 1933 February (Box 1)
    - Brain & Brain, solicitors, 1930 August 13 (Box 1)
    - Bridges, Robert Seymour, 1844-1930, 1911 January, 1910 November (Box 1)
    - Brittain, Robert Edward, 1908-, 1938 October-December (Box 1)
    - Brooke, Charles Frederick Tucker, 1883-1946, 1939 December (Box 1)
    - Brooks, Eric St. John, 1883-1955, 1928 June- 1937 December (Box 1)
    - Bryant, Arthus, 1899-, 1938 August (Box 1)
    - Camps, William Anthony, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, Harry James, bp. of Oxford, 1901-, no year August 7 (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, Joseph Estlin, 1844-1927, 1926 August (Box 1)
    - Carwardine Probert, William Geoffrey, 1864-1938, July 1937- November 1939 (Box 1)
    - Castley, Roger Cuthbert, no year June 5 (Box 1)
    - Champion, George James, no year September (Box 1)
    - Chapman, Robert William, 1881-1960, 1938 February (Box 1)
    - Church, Richard Thomas, 1893-, 1933 January (Box 1)
    - Coghill, Neville, 1899-, 1938 May (Box 1)
    - Coldstream, F M, 1937 March-1941 (Box 1)
    - Coppard, Alfred Edgar, 1878-1957, 1930 October (Box 1)
    - Crewe, Robert Offley Ashburton Crew-Milnes, 1st marquis of, 1858-1945, 1939 April-August (Box 1)
    - D'Arcy, Martin Cyril, 1888-, 1934 April (Box 1)
    - Daubney, Robert Henry, undated (Box 1)
    - De la Mare, Walter John, 1873-1956, 1923 February -1936 June (Box 1)
    - De Labilliere, Paul Fulerand Delacour, 1879-1946, 1939 March (Box 1)
    - Donaldson, St. Claire George Alfred, bp. of Salisbury, 1863-1935, 1926 December (Box 1)
    - Eliot, Thomas Stearns, 1885-1965, 1927-1938; 3 (Box 2)
      Includes a typescript of "Ash Wednesday."
    - Elton, Oliver, 1861-1945, 1937 November-1939 January (Box 2)
    - Faber, Sir Geoffrey Cust, 1889-1961, 1933 March (Box 2)
    - Farquharson, Arthur Spenser Loat, d. 1942, 1930 March (Box 2)
    - Fasnacht, George Eugene, 1934 November (Box 2)
    - Fevard, Arthur George, 1858-1943, 1938 July (Box 2)
    - Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1883-1945, undated (Box 2)
    - Flew, Robert Newton, 1886-1962, 1933 March (Box 2)
    - Fox, Eleanor, 1936 April-1937 December (Box 2)
    - Gaskell, Dorothy (Bagot), 1940 August, undated (Box 2)
    - Gerhardi, William Alexander, 1895-, 1925 December (Box 2)
    - Golding, Louis, 1895-1958, 1922-1934 (Box 2)
    - Grece, Clair Mansell Maybury, 1937 July (Box 2)
    - Gwatkin, Henry Melvill, 1844-1916, 1916 July-September (Box 2)
    - Gwyer, John, 1938 December (Box 2)
    - Hanson, Laurence William, d. 1966, 1930 May (Box 2)
    - Harding, Alfred, bp. of Washington, 1852-1923, 1917 July (Box 2)
    - Hart-Davis, Sir Rupert Charles, 1907-, 1938 January-December (Box 2)
    - Hennings, Richard Owen, 1911-, 1938 September (Box 2)
    - Henson, Herbert Hensley, bp. of Durham, 1863-1947, 1933 March-April (Box 2)
    - Hodge, Alan, 1915-, 1935 February (Box 2)
    - Holt, Henry & Co., publishers, 1939 September (Box 2)
    - Hutchinson, Francis Ernest, 1871-1947, 1936 November-1937 August (Box 2)
    - Jacot, Emile, 1925 August, 1926 October (Box 2)
    - James, Montagu Rhodes, 1862-1936, 1926 January (Box 2)
    - Janelle, Pierre, 1936 September, 1937 September (Box 2)
    - Jerrold, Douglas, 1893-1964, 1935 January (Box 2)
    - Kernahan, Coulson, 1858-1943, undated (Box 2)
    - Krishna, Mitra, Nil, 1938 August (Box 2)
    - Lang, Andrew, 1844-1912, 1909 October (Box 2)
    - Leveson-Gower, Sir George Granville, 1858-1951, 1936-1952 (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Clive Staples, 1898-1963, 1937 August (Box 2)
    - Lighton, Digby, 1919 June (Box 2)
    - Loewe, Herbert Martin James, 1882-1940, 1938 January (Box 2)
    - Longmans Green & Co., publishers, 1937 August-December (Box 2)
    - Lynd, Robert Wilson, 1879-1949, undated (Box 2)
    - Lys, Francis John, 1863-1947, 1930-1933 (Box 2)
    - Macan, Reginald Walter, 1848-1941, 1938 May (Box 2)
    - Macartney, Maxwell Henry Hayes, 1936 August (Box 2)
    - McConnell, James R., 1909 January-1915 March (Box 2)
    - MacDonald, Hugh, 1885-1958, 1929 December-1937 March (Box 2)
    - McKim, Randolph Harrison, 1842-1921, 1915 May (Box 2)
    - Major, Henry Dewsbury Alves, 1871-1961, 1917 April-1938 October (Box 2)
    - Martin, David, brother, 1901-, 1943 July (Box 2)
    - Martz, Louis Lohr, 1913-, 1955 July (Box 2)
    - Masefield, Constance (de la Cherois-Crommelin), d. 1960, undated (Box 2)
    - Masefield, John, 1878-1967, undated (Box 2)
    - Massingham, Harold John, 1888-, 1936 March-1939 October (Box 2)
    - Megroz, Rodolphe Louis, 1891-1968, undated (Box 2)
    - Miller, Thomas Woodnutt, 1886, 1912 November -1915 September (Box 2)
    - Morley, Frank Vigor, 1899-, 1933 March-1938 August (Box 2)
    - Money-Kyrle, Rowland Tracy Ashe, d. 1928, 1922 March-1926 August (Box 2)
    - Monro, Harold, 1879-1932, 1913 November (Box 2)
    - Morrell, Lady Ottoline Violet Anne (Cavendish-Bentick), 1873-1938, 1933 January (Box 2)
    - Moult, Thomas, 1927 December (Box 2)
    - Munro, John Arthur Ruskin, 1864-1944, 1934 March-1935 December (Box 2)
    - Murray, David Leslie, 1888-1962, 1932 December-1934 November (Box 2)
    - Nash, Philip Ernest, undated (Box 2)
    - Newdigate, Bernard Henry, 1869-1944, 1938 April (Box 2)
    - Noyes, Alfred, 1880-1958, 1911 March (Box 2)
    - Osborn, James Marshall, 1906-, 1935 October-1940 February (Box 2)
    - Osgood, Charles Grosvenor, 1871-1964, 1940 November (Box 2)
    - Paris, Herbert John, 1938 October (Box 3)
    - Parker, James Leslie, undated (Box 3)
    - Patton, John Shelton, 1857-1932, 1922 July-September (Box 3)
    - Percival, John, bp. of Hereford, 1934-1918, 1916 July (Box 3)
    - Pitt-Rivers, George Henry Lane Fox, 1890-1966, 1928 December, 1929 March (Box 3)
    - Porter, Alan, 1899-1942, 1921 July-1932 October (Box 3)
    - Pott, Gladys Sydney, 1867-1961, 1920 May (Box 3)
    - Pott, John Arthur, 1865-1920, 1920 March (Box 3)
    - Rawson, Frederick Lawrence, 1859-, 1916 December (Box 3)
    - Reed, Stanley Forman, 1884-, 1948 October, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Rennell, James Rennell Rodd, baron, 1858-1941, 1932 September-1939 August (Box 3)
    - Richmond, Sir Bruce Lyttelton, March 1937 (Box 3)
    - Roberts, Paul Ernest, 1873-1949, 1933 August-1939 January (Box 3)
    - Rogers, Neville, 1952 February (Box 3)
    - Ryle, Gilbert, 1900-, undated (Box 3)
    - Sassoon, Siegfried, 1886-1967, 1927 January, 1933 January (Box 3)
    - Scott, Maeve (Jacot), 1926 May-1930 July (Box 3)
    - Sencourt, Robert, 1890-, 1923-1940 (Box 3)
    - Sherburn, George Wiley, 1884-, 1939 December, 1940 October (Box 3)
    - Simpson, David Capell, 1883-1962, 1934 November; 2 (Box 3)
    - Simpson, Percy, 1865-1962, 1937 April (Box 3)
    - Sitwell, Dame Edith, 1887-1964, 1939 July (Box 3)
    - Smart, Dorothy, 1937 November-1936 March (Box 3)
    - Smith, David Nichol, 1875-1962, 1938 July (Box 3)
    - Smith, Ronald Gregor, 1913-1968, 1937 July (Box 3)
    - Smith-Dampier, John Lewis Dampier, 1938 March-1939 December (Box 3)
    - Society of Authors, London, 1912 January (Box 3)
    - Somerset, Henry Vere Fitzroy, 1921 February-1939 October (Box 3)
    - Squire, Sir John Collings, 1884-1958, undated (Box 3)
    - Stead, William Force, 1884-1967, 1920-1951; 4 (Box 3)
    - Stevenson, Burton Egbert, 1872-, 1911 February (Box 3)
    - Stewart, Dom Benedict, 1938 February (Box 3)
    - Streeter, Burnett Hillman, 1874-1937, 1925-1934 (Box 3)
    - Strong, Leonard Alfred George, 1896-1958, 1924 June (Box 3)
    - Strong, May A., 1938 May-September (Box 3)
    - Sturm, Frank Pearce, 1879-1942, 1938 April-May (Box 3)
    - Sutherland, James Runcieman, 1900-, 1934 November (Box 3)
    - Swayne, William Shuckburgh, bp. of Lincoln, 1862-1941, 1926 January (Box 3)
    - Taylor, Samuel Mac, 1856-1916, 1912 November (Box 3)
    - Tomlinson, Philip, d. 1955, 1930-1955 (Box 3)
    - Tweedsmuir, Susan Charlotte (Grosvenor) Buchan, baroness, 1882-, 1933-1952 (Box 3)
    - Underhill, Evelyn, 1875-1941, 1933 January (Box 3)
    - Valentine, Edward Abram Uffington, 1870-, 1902 August (Box 3)
    - Vosburgh, Royden Woodward, 1927 February (Box 3)
    - Walpole, Sir Hugh Seymour, 1884-1941, 1935 August (Box 3)
    - Ward, James, 1843-1925, 1923 August (Box 3)
    - Washington, Horace Lee, 1864-, 1915 July-1917 December (Box 3)
    - Whitridge, Arnold, 1891-, 1933 March (Box 3)
    - Wilkinson, Cyril Hackett, 1888-1960, 1935 October, 1940 May (Box 3)
    - Wolfe, Humbert, 1885-1940, undated (Box 3)
    - Wood, Evelyn, 1931 December (Box 3)
    - Wright, Bernard Arker, 1893-, 1934 November-December (Box 3)
    - Yeats, George (Hyde Lees), 1935, undated (Box 3)
    - Yeats, William Butler, 1865-1939, 1921-1939; 2 (Box 3)
    - Yeats-Brown, Francis Charles Claypon, 1886-, 1933 January (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence
    - A, 1924-1940, undated (Box 4)
    - B, 1910-1938 (Box 4)
    - C, 1911-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - D, 1908-1938 (Box 4)
    - E, 1903-1939 (Box 4)
    - F, 1926-1939, undated (Box 4)
    - G, 1909-1927, undated (Box 4)
    - H, 1903-1954, undated (Box 4)
    - J-K, 1903-1930, undated (Box 4)
    - L, 1902-1961, undated (Box 4)
    - M, 1910-1940, undated (Box 4)
    - O, 1931-1936, undated (Box 4)
    - P, 1909-1931 (Box 4)
    - R, 1911-1938, undated (Box 4)
    - S, 1913-1962, undated (Box 4)
    - T-U, 1909-1935 (Box 4)
    - W, 1909-1939, undated (Box 4)
    - Y, 1915, undated (Box 4)
    - Unidentified, 1927 November 7 (Box 4)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Browne, Mary Helen Scott, 1904-1905; 2 (Box 5)
    - Donaldson, Charlotte (later Hemphill), 1909-1924; 2 (Box 5)
    - Donaldson, Charlotte (later Hemphill), 1909-1924 (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, 1914-1933, undated (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, Arthur T., 1914-1915, undated (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, Edmund K., 1914-1928, undated (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, Fitzhugh Coyle, brother-in-law of WFS -1911, 1909 August 31 (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, Julia, undated (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, Mary Farr (Coyle), 1910-1929, undated (Box 6)
    - Goldsborough, William F., 1909-1912 (Box 6)
    - Hunter, Margaret Canmont (Force), cousin of WFS, 1868-, 1909-1968 (Box 6)
    - Moffatt, Ruby, 1918 (Box 6)
    - Osborn, James Marshall, 1936-1963, undated; 3 (Box 6)
    - Stead, Anne Frances Goldsborough, 1906-1910; 6 (Box 7)
    - Stead, Anne Frances Goldsborough, 1910-1930; 6 (Box 8)
    - Stead, Anne Frances Goldsborough, 1928-1951, undated; 6 (Box 9)
    - Stead, Cynthia Force, "Innie" 1853-1918, 1905-1911 (Box 9)
    - Stead, Cynthia Force, "Innie" 1853-1918, 6 (Box 10)
    - Stead, Edward, 1895-, 1909-1971; 6 (Box 11)
    - Stead, Edward, 1895, 1909-1938; 4 (Box 12)
    - Stead, Edward Briggs, 1833-1912, 1904 April 1 (Box 12)
    - Stead, Manning Force, 1908-1937, 1959 January 18; 2 (Box 13)
    - Stead, Dom Julian (Peter Force Stead), son of WFS, 1926-, 1932-1961; 3 (Box 13)
    - Stead, Philip Hugh Force, 1913-, 1939-1959; 2 (Box 13)
    - Stead, Robert (brother of WFS), 1886-, 1903-1953 (Box 13)
    - Stead, Robert (father of WFS), 1856-, 1901-1943; 2 (Box 13)
    - Stead, Robert (father of WFS), 1856-, 1901-1943 (Box 14)
    - Stead, William Force, 1917-1964, undated; 13 (Box 14)
    - Tottie, Monica R., 1939-1946, undated (Box 15)
    - Trafford, Cicily, 1908-, 1918-1955; 2 (Box 15)
    - Trafford, Dorothy Molfatt, 1886-, 1922, undated (Box 15)
    - Trafford, John Lionel, 1924-, undated (Box 15)
    - Worthington, Mary (Stead), sister of WFS, 1889-, 1909-1939, undated; 3 (Box 15)
- Writings, 1899-1963; Series II; 6.05; (19 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries: Prose Works, Poetry, and Sermons, but is otherwise unarranged.
  The series contains contains notes, drafts, manuscripts, typescripts and other materials for prose works, poetry, and sermons. The folders with titles beginning with "Stead" appear to contain drafts and notes for an unpublished memoir. Other material includes the finished typescript of Stead's M.A. thesis, Robert Southwell; two boxes of draft of a personal meditation on religious belief in the modern world, God's Great Secret - A Pilgrimage; and an elaborately written volume of juvenile poetry, The Poetical Works of William Force Stead.
  This series contains only those writings by Stead that were acquired and identified as such in 1969. Other writings by Stead are located in Series III, Notebooks, and Series VII and Series X. Many of the items in Series XI, Printed Materials, are also works by Stead.
  - Prose Works
    - Christopher Smart, undated (Box 16)
    - God's Great Secret - A Pilgrimage, undated; 3 (Box 17)
    - God's Great Secret - A Pilgrimage, undated; 2 (Box 18)
    - "Stead - On W. B. Yeats", 1939 May 10 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - Response to the questions for 'Character Analysis'", 1938-1940 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - On T. S. Eliot", 1940 April 30 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - The Wives of the Poets", 1962 December 18 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - On Edmund Blunden", 1940 May 10 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - Lady Ottoline Morrell", 1938 May 13 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - Oxford Ignorance", 1938 October 27 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - ALS to Edward Stead", 1931 August 4 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - Frank Prewett, etc, 1938 May 11 (Box 19)
    - Stead - On Belloe and Chesterton...", 1939 November 24 (Box 19)
    - "Stead - on Roy Campbell, Lord David Cecil, encore on Chesterton, AE Coppard", 1940 January 31 (Box 19)
    - Robert Southwell, 1936 April 17, undated; 4 (Box 20)
    - Robert Southwell, undated; 3 (Box 21)
    - Robert Southwell, 1936 April 17, undated (Box 22)
    - "Music (WFS)", 1945 (Box 22)
    - "Oxford Poets: holograph", 1954 (Box 22)
    - "In Galilee: typescript", 1963 December 1963 (Box 22)
    - "Essay on Edgar Allan Poe", 1920 November, 1921 August 22 (Box 22)
    - "Stead on Edmund Blunden (draft)", undated (Box 22)
    - "Prose works dated", 1899-1935; 2 (Box 22)